Guide to the Daniel Webster Crofts Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Daniel Webster Crofts Papers
1892-2008
1892-1950
RG 240
Yale University Divinity School Library
1
(2 boxes)
Letters and writings document the life and work of Daniel Webster Crofts, an American missionary serving under the China Inland Mission, primarily in Guizhou Province, China from 1895 to 1944. Detailed letters written to the Crofts children describe the evangelization and literature distribution work of Crofts and his first wife Verna Hammarén Crofts and his second wife Mabel Harlow Crofts, as well as their way of life in a rural area beset by famine, and political disruption.
Crofts, Daniel Webster, 1866-1960
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Daniel Wallace Crofts, 2011
Biographical / Historical
Chronology of Daniel Webster Crofts
1866 Aug 20 Daniel Webster Crofts born in Ohio, son of John Byron Crofts and Hannah Kane Crofts. The Crofts had eleven children, ten of whom survived to adulthood: sons Frank, Daniel, Will, Rob, Jim, Tom and daughters Jennie, Ada, Minnie, and Mary.
1891 Graduated from Muskingum College
1894 Graduated from Chicago Theological Seminary
1895 While working as minister for a congregation in Peoria, Illinois, applied to become missionary of China Inland Mission.
1895 Dec 16 Arrived in Shanghai, having left Tacoma, Washington in November, and stopping in Japan. Began language study.
1896 - 1901 Stationed in Laohekou, Hubei Province
1899 Nov Married Verna Hammarén, a missionary sponsored by the Free Church of Finland working under the direction of the China Inland Mission
1900 Sep 13 Son John born in Shanghai where Verna had evacuated due to Boxer Rebellion. Daniel arrived in Shanghai in November.
1901 After being refugees in Shanghai for several months, lived in Yangzhou and Zhenjiang before returning to Laohekou
1902 Feb 8 Daughter Verna born in Hankou. Shortly thereafter the family went on furlough, first to Finland and then to the U.S.
1903 August 2 Son Alfred born in Oakland, California. Shortly thereafter the family returned to China, arriving in Shanghai in September
1904 Apr Established new CIM mission in Zhenyuan, Guizhou Province. Crofts' missionary work involved itinerations through countryside to preach and sell books.
1906 Sep 20 Daughter Saima born.
1908 - 1911 Crofts contributed reports and columns to the North-China Herald
1909 Son John and daughter Verna traveled to boarding school at Chefoo School in Yantai, Shandong, accompanied by wife Verna and son Alfred. Verna died in Chefoo from dysentery and weak heart. Daniel traveled to Chefoo and spent winter with children before returning to Guizhou.
1912 Saima joined her older siblings at Chefoo School, having earlier lived with a missionary family in Panghai following her mother's death.
1915-1917 Crofts worked with fellow missionary M. H. Hutton in Panghai, using it as a base to work with Black Miao people.
1917 Escorted son John to U.S. to enroll him in college, returning to China in fall of 1918
1919 Aug Married Mabel Harlow, CIM missionary based in Chefoo. They returned to Guizhou, stationed in Zunyi, while two middle children went to U.S. and Saima remained at Chefoo.
1922 Opened new mission station in Qianxi, in northwest Guizhou.
1925-1926 Furlough in U.S.
1927-1936 Following furlough, Daniel and Mabel Crofts initially stayed in Shanghai, due to political disturbances in the interior, but in July 1928 moved to Zhenjiang and from late 1928 were stationed in Qanxi. In 1935-1936 the approach of Communist troops caused them to evacuate from Qanxi to Sichuan Province.
1936-1938 Furlough in the U.S.
1938 Nov-1944 Returned to China and were stationed in Qianxi, Guizhou
1942 Feb Mabel Crofts died of typhoid
1944 Daniel Crofts left China and after visiting various relatives settled in Florida
1960 Jun 14 Crofts died
For additional biographical information see book published by Crofts' grandson Daniel W. Crofts: Upstream Odyssey: An American in China, 1895-1944 (Norwalk, CT: Eastbridge, 2008).
Scope and Contents
This collection primarily consists of regular, detailed letters written by Daniel Webster Crofts or his second wife Mabel Harlow Crofts to the four Crofts children who from an early age were separated from their parents at boarding school in Chefoo, and then in the U.S. The original format letters in the collection are complemented by scans of some additional documents, as well as the detailed, scholarly biography of Crofts written by his grandson Daniel Webster Crofts, a copy of which is in the Divinity Library's cataloged collection. Series I, Correspondence, is primarily family correspondence with a few folders of non-family letters. Series II, Writings, contains clippings of articles written by Daniel Crofts for the North-China Herald. Series III, Biographical Documentation, contains a few documents regarding the Crofts family and Crofts' wives. Much more detailed information is available in the biography noted above.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence
II. Writings
III. Biographical Documentation
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Missions -- China; Crofts, Daniel Webster, 1866-1960; China Inland Mission
- Correspondence, 1892-2008
  - CD containing PDF scans of letters and other documents contained in this collection plus some for which the originals are no longer available. Information regarding "Upstream Odyssey: An American in China, 1895-1944" by Daniel Wallace Crofts, grandson of Daniel Webster Crofts, 1892-2008 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Family correspondence
    - To extended family
      - Primarily from DWC to siblings, written from Chenyuan [Zhenyuan], Chefoo, Kiensi [Qianxi], Palatka, 1907-1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - To children
      Scope and Contents
      Letters to children are primarily from Daniel Crofts, with some from second wife Mabel.
      - Letters to children at school in Chefoo from DWC in Panghai and Chenyuan and while on trip to U.S. in late 1917, 1916 Jul - 1918 Dec (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Letters to children, some of whom are in the U.S. at school, 1919 Feb-Dec (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Incl. re. trip to Finland and U.S. and return to China, 1924 May - 1926 Dec (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Written from Shanghai while waiting for permission to return to Guizhou, 1927 Feb - 1928 Dec (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Incl. re. daily life at Kiensi [Qianxi] station, 1929 Feb-Dec (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Primarily from Kiensi; incl. re. trip escorting new missionaries to Chungking, building, medical work, 1930 Jan - 1931 Apr (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Primarily from Kiensi; incl. re. civil war conditions; traveling to meetings, 1931 Jun - 1932 Feb (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Primarily from Kiensi; incl. re. concerns for children's needs during Depression in U.S., 1932 Mar-Dec (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Primarily from Kiensi; incl. re. robberies, political unrest, country tour, 1933 Jan-Sep (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Primarily from Kiensi; incl. re. month's visit to Sinchang, new outstation, 1933 Oct - 1934 May (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Primarily from Kiensi; incl. re. country travels, Bible school, 1934 Jun-Sep (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Primarily from Kiensi; Communist troubles; travel, 1934 Oct - 1935 Nov (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Furlough in U.S., England, Finland - visiting family and friends, 1936 Mar - 1937 Dec (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Furlough in U.S. and return to China, 1938 May-Oct (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Re. return to mission work, with time spent in Tushan, Kweiyang, and Kiensi; repair to house in Kiensi, 1939 Feb-May (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Re. mission work in Kiensi, 1939 Jun-Nov (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Incl. re. time spent in Kopu [Gebu] teaching classes for church workers, 1940 Feb-Jun (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Incl. re. daily life in Kiensi, opinions re. war in Europe, 1940 Jul-Aug (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - DWC distributing tracts and Bible; medical treatment of soldiers and others, 1940 Sep-Dec (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Incl. re. attendance at conference in Kweiyang [Guiyang], high prices, dispensing medicines, 1941 Jun-Jul (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Government motor school established in Kiensi, leading to large influx of soldiers; tract ministry, 1941 Aug-Nov (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - Incl. re. death of Mabel; DWC goes to Kweiyang, then Pingpa [Pingba] before return to Kiensi, 1942 Jan-Dec (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - DWC's daily life in Kiensi, teaching English to Chinese men, joined by missionary family, 1943 Jan-Dec (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - Making preparations to leave China; begins journey to U.S. via India, 1944 Feb-Dec (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - Arrives in California, traveling in U.S. and Canada, 1945 Feb-Sep (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - Continues travels, visiting friends and family, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - Settles in Jacksonville, Florida with sister and after her death in Palatka with daughter Saima and family, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - In Palatka, assisting with Saima and family with chicken business, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 30)
      - In Palatka and travels west, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - In Palatka and traveling, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - General correspondence
    - Circular letters
      - Typed excerpts of circular letters and diary entries of Verna Hammarén, stationed in Chinkiang [Zhenjiang], 1893-1897 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - To/from others
      - Incl. to/from Wilkinson, Lagerquist, Solomon, Houghton, Cook, 1937-1956 (Box 2, Folder 34)
      - Letter from Robert Chang to Rev. Yong, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Writings, 1933-1934
  - News articles written by DWC while stationed in Kiensi [Qianxi], including regarding famine, opium, bandits, 1933-1934 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Biographical Documentation, 1942-1955
  - Incl. re. Crofts family history, biographical sketch re. Verna Hammarén, death certificate of Catherine Mabel Harlow Crofts, lists of household items, 1942-1955, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Collected material: cards, clippings, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 38)